Guide to the David Goodstein papers, [ca. 1954-1985]
Goodstein, David papers, [ca. 1954-1985]
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
David B. Goodstein papers, 1954-1985
7311
David B. Goodstein, 1932-1985
4.7 cubic ft.
Diaries (datebooks), personal files, military records, correspondence, interview transcripts, lists, financial papers, photographs, slides, films, videotapes, media survey, obituary.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
The David B. Goodstein collection includes documents related to Goodstein's role as a spokesperson for the gay rights movement, the Concerned Voters of California's response to the anti-gay Briggs Initiative, the "Advocate Experience," and Dade County's anti-gay activity. Also includes personal papers (certificates, diplomas, military documents, etc.) as well as photographs and slides of show horses and fine art and of Goodstein and his friends.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
David Goodstein was born in Denver, Colorado in 1932. After graduating from Cornell University in 1954 he earned an LLB degree from Columbia University. He practiced for a time in New York City as a criminal attorney. In 1960 his career moved to Wall Street, where he founded Compufund, a mutual fund that introduced statistical analysis of common stocks using computers. During this period, Goodstein became involved in social issues, serving on the boards of Grand Street Settlement Houses and the United Settlement Houses of New York, and Cornell University's Special Education Program for racial minorities. While in New York City, he served on the Cornell University Council, and was president of the Friends of the Andrew D. White Museum. He was a collector and dealer of art, and with his brother Edward, established one of the finest collections of Italian Baroque painting in the United States. Goodstein was also an avid amateur horseman and American Saddlebred Horse owner and exhibitor. Goodstein moved to California in 1971 and there became active in the gay rights movement and the California Democratic party. He was instrumental in attaining the passage of California's consensual sex legislation in 1974, and was responsible for the creation of the Gay Rights National Lobby in 1976. He was a co-founder of Concerned Voters of California, a gay rights group which helped defeat a 1978 initiative that would have banned homosexuals from teaching or working in public schools. In the early 1980s, Goodstein made a highly successful national tour to establish a network of gay political fundraisers. He was also the founder and chairman of the Whitman-Radclyffe Foundation, a gay service organization dealing with drug abuse. In 1975 Goodstein bought the Advocate, a Los Angeles-based gay magazine. Within ten years it was the largest circulation gay news magazine in the country. He served as president of Liberation Publications, Inc., publisher of the Advocate. He also founded the "Advocate Experience," an EST-derived workshop designed primarily for gays and lesbians. He also served as a member of the National Democratic Finance Council, the California State Democratic Central Committee, and the Hunger Project Council. Goodstein died on 22 June 1985 of complications arising from cancer.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The collection consists of correspondence (1975-1979 only), address and date books (1968-1979 only), biographical and publicity press releases, interview transcripts, itineraries, clippings, military documents and certificates, brochures, membership and contributor lists, financial statements, photographic prints and negatives, slides, videotapes, audiotapes, and plaques.
Subjects include David Goodstein's publishing of the Advocate, his interviews with political leaders pertaining to gay rights and activism issues, and his role as a spokesperson and leader of the gay rights movement, in which capacity he traveled widely in the United States establishing political contacts. A main issue is the Concerned Voters of California's response to the anti-gay "Briggs Initiative," in which Goodstein was involved. Other subjects include the "Advocate Experience," the John Tunney election campaign, a gay retirement center, the Privacy Act, and Dade Count, Florida's anti-gay activity. There are many photographs and slides of show horses and fine art, and of Goodstein and his friends at Cornell University, and traveling in the United States and abroad. The correspondence is sometime accompanied by an index to the correspondents. Persons figuring prominently in the collection include Art Agnos, John Tunney, Werner Erhard, and in interviews, Pete McCloskey, Percy Sutton, John Burton, Leo Ryan, and Edward Koch.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Goodstein, David B.; Agnos, Art.; Tunney, John.; Erhard, Werner.; McCloskey, Pete.; Sutton, Percy.; Burton, John.; Ryan, Leo.; Koch, Edward.; Brown, Jerry.; Concerned Voters of California.; Whitman-Radclyffe Foundation.; Democratic National Committee.
Subjects:
Advocate.; Gays.; Gay Liberation Movement.; Homosexuality.; Homosexuality--Laws and legislation.; Homophobia--Dave County, Florida.; Homophobia--California.; Show horses.
Form and Genre Terms:
Diaries.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIAL
Advocate Research and Education Foundation/Advocate Experience Records, #7310.
COLLECTION ARRANGEMENT
The collection is evidently only a selection of Goodstein's files and holdings. Arrangement is basically by form of material.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Address and Note books
Series II. Correspondence
Series III. Subject Files
Series IV. Photographic Prints
Series V. Photographic Negatives
Series VI. Slides
Series VII. Video/audio tapes, films, and miscellaneous
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Address and Note books
  - Address Books
    - Address Book A-K, c. 1968-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Address Book L-Z, c. 1968-1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Address Book A-N, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Address Book O-Z, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Datebooks and Desk Calendar
    - Datebook, 1 JAN - 30 JUN 1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Datebook, 1 JUL - 31 DEC 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Desk Calendar, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Datebook, 1 JAN - 30 JUN 1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Datebook, 1 JUL - 31 DEC 1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Datebook, 1 JAN - 30 JUN 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Datebook, 1 JUL - 31 DEC 1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Datebook, 31 DEC 1977 - 30 JUN 1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Datebook, 1 JUL - 31 DEC 1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Datebook, 1 OCT - 30 DEC 1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Datebook, 1 JAN - 31 MAR 1979 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Datebook, 1 MAR - 30 APR 1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Datebook, 2 MAY - 30 JUN 1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Datebook, 1 JUL - 31 AUG 1979 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Datebook, 1 SEP - 31 OCT 1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Datebook, 1 NOV - 31 DEC 1979 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Datebook, 1 JAN - 29 FEB 1980 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Datebook, 1 MAR - 30 APR 1980 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Datebook, 1 MAY - 30 JUN 1980 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Datebook, 1 JUL - 31 AUG 1980 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Datebook, 1 SEP - 31 OCT 1980 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Datebook, 1 NOV - 31 DEC 1980 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Datebook, 1 JAN - 28 FEB 1981 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Datebook, 1 MAR - 30 APR 1981 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Datebook, 1 MAY - 30 JUN 1981 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Datebook, 1 JUL - 31 AUG 1981 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Datebook, 1 SEP - 31 OCT 1981 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Datebook, 1 NOV - 31 DEC 1981 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Datebook, 1 JAN - 30 JUN 1982 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Datebook, 1 JUL - 31 DEC 1982 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Datebook, 1 JAN - 30 JUN 1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Datebook, 1 JUL - 31 DEC 1983 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Datebook, 1 JAN - 31 MAY 1984 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Datebook, 1 JAN - OCT 1985 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - List of names and addresses, diet, and miscellany, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Address book; phone registry, c. 1970 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series II. Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 20 FEB - 30 APR 1975 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1 MAY - 31 JUL 1975 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1 AUG - 29 SEP 1975 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1 OCT - 29 DEC 1975 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 2 JAN - 29 MAR 1976 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1 APR - 30 JUL 1976 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 4 AUG - 23 DEC 1976 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 4 JAN - 1 JUL 1977 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 17 OCT - 6 DEC 1977 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Chron File Index, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 2 JAN - 27 FEB 1978 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1 MAR - 28 JUN 1978 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1 JUL - 31 AUG 1978 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, 1 SEP - 29 SEP 1978 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, 1 OCT - 31 OCT 1978 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, 1 NOV - 30 NOV 1978 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1 DEC - 13 DEC 1978 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 13 DEC - 29 DEC 1978 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, 2 JAN - 25 JAN 1979 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, 2 FEB - 27 FEB 1979 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, 1 MAR - 27 APR 1979 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, 7 MAY - 28 JUN 1979 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence, 5 JUL - 28 SEP 1979 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, 2 OCT - 26 DEC 1979 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Personal Correspondence Index, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Advocate letter to Gay Men's Health Crisis, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Series III. Subject Files
  - David B. Goodstein (Goodstein) Biographical Notes and Press Kit, 1983 and n.d. (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Goodstein Obituaries, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Goodstein Obituary and Photographs, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Photograph: Goodstein and Jimmy Carter, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Photograph: Abby Van Buren, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - "Kazoo Night" - Birthday drawing for Goodstein by Jim Corty, 11 JUN 1980 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Goodstein Interviews with Pete McCloskey, Percy Sutton, John Burton, Leo Ryan, and "R", 1977 and n.d. (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Houston Interview Schedule, c. 1977 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - United States Army Reserve Officer Commissioning Certificate, 1954, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Itinerary, Washington D.C., 2 FEB 1977 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Los Angeles Interview Schedules, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Midwest Itinerary and Correspondence, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - New York City Itinerary and Correspondence, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - New York City Itinerary and Correspondence, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - California Trip Itinerary and Correspondence, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - San Diego, San Francisco Trip Itineraries, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - San Diego Trip, MAY, JUN 1977 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Goodstein Publicity, Including Articles in The Boston Phoenix, Bay Area Reporter, and Update, 1977-1985 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Goodstein Publicity, 1975-1985 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Goodstein Publicity - Horse World Magazine, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Goodstein Publicity - Superliving, and Public Relations, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence and Photograph from The Review, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Keith Irvine Correspondence to Edward C. Goodstein, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Goodstein Publicity - Saddle and Bridle, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "The Goodstein Report - The Awareness of David Goodstein and the Advocate by the Gay Press, and General Media and Policy Makers," by the Eileen Prescott Company, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Oklahoma Speaking Tour, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - New York City Speaking Schedule, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Goodstein Military Discharge Papers, 1955-1962 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Winner/Wagner and Associates and the Briggs Initiative, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Winner/Wagner and Associates Correspondence, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Briggs Initiative Correspondence, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Art Agnos and the Briggs Initiative, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 23-24)
  - Bay Area Committee Against the Briggs Initiative (BACABI), c. 1978 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Concerned Voters of California (CVC) Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - CVC Financial Statements, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Questionnaire for Contributors of Fifty Dollars or more to CVC, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - CVC Financial (see also CVC Materials), c. 1975 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - John Tunney Campaign Correspondence, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Tunney Fundraiser, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Tunney Campaign(see also Tunney Campaign Materials), 1976 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Don Bradley re: CVC and the Briggs Imitative, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Advocate Experience Intensive Facilitators Manual, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Advocate Experience, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Douglas K. Freeman and the Kinsey Institute for Research in Sex, Gender, and Reproduction, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Dade County Donations, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Dade County Mailing List, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Political Mailing Lists, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - "Money Management - Basic Rules of Financial Health," by David B. Goodstein, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Legislation, 1975-1978 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - David Bryant Correspondence - Privacy Act, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Werner Erhard - EST Correspondence, 1976-79 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Breakthrough Racing Correspondence, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - New Alliance for Gay Equality (New AGE), 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Washington Story - Goodstein Interview with Edward Koch, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - James W. Graves and the Montrose Activity Center, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Gay Retirement Center, 1976-1978 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Advocate Coverage of the 1976 Elections, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - One Inc./Institute for the Study of Human Resources, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Goodstein's Cornell diploma, Bachelor of Arts, 1944 (Mapcase-folder 1)
  - CVC (Concerned Voters of California) Materials
    - CVC Mailing Lists, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - CVC Expenditures, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - CVC Financial, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - CVC - Briggs Initiative, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Briggs Supporters Mass Mailings, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Briggs/Proposition 6: Initiative, Legal Papers, Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Privacy Act, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Privacy Act - Drafts, c. 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Anti-Recidivism and Post Release Services Task Force, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Tunney Campaign Materials
    - Tunney Fundraiser Master Mailing List, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Tunney Campaign Mailing Lists, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Burt Pines Reception, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Political Mailing Lists re: Dade County, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Blue Flettrich's List, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Series IV. Photographic Prints
  - Goodstein personal photos, c.1956-c.1985; Includes photographs of friends, dogs and horses, travel pictures, houses, and miscellaneous people and places. Several are identified. (Box 6-7)
  - Horses, n.d.; Includes many photos of Goodstein riding, at shows, and with horses and horse people. Few are identified. (Box 8)
- Series V. Photographic Negatives
  - Photographic Negatives, n.d.; Presumably negatives of the prints in Boxes 6-8 (Box 9)
- Series VI. Slides
  - Goodstein at Cornell University, and on trips in Florida, Hawaii, and in Europe, 1950-1959; Eleven metal slide boxes; Also, slides of friends, boys, and "Bruce of Hollywood." All are identified. (Box 10)
  - European trip, 1964; Two plastic slide cases; All are identified. (Box 10)
  - Objets d'art, works of art, furniture, One case of 2.5 x 2.5 slides (Box 10)
  - 1950s at Cornell University, and 1950s-1980s, 1950s-1980s; Two boxes of slides (Box 11)
- Series VII. Video/audio tapes, films, and miscellaneous
  - Mike Ferrell, Human Rights Campaign Fund (HRCF), n.d.; Three U-matic videocassette tapes (Box 11)
  - Mike Ferrell HRCF, "Be All That You Are" with Terry Cole Whittaker Ministries, and one unidentified, Three VHS videocassette tapes (Box 11)
  - David B. Goodstein Memorial Service, 28 JULY 1985; Two audiocassettes (Box 11)
  - Unidentified, Three 8mm films (Box 11)
  - Award Plaques to Goodstein, 1984-1985; The Business and Professional Association of Los Angeles, 1985; the 1984 Vis Ã Vis Award "In Recognition of Dedicated Service and Exemplary Courage to Secure Individual Freedoms and Guarantee Humanity Its Inalienable Rights" (Box 11)
  - Pornography, Eleven films (Box 11)